hello everyone this is me in a hotel
room as you know i'm traveling this week
i could not do a live stream so i
thought let me take a break from
proceedings and answer some of your
questions do an ask a budget show let's
record it and release it as soon as i
can
so that's what this is about i'm going
to answer a few questions that you've
asked me and let's begin with question
number one
it's by anubhav bharadwaj
i have read that most of the casualties
in world war ii happened on the eastern
front around 80 of the hitler nazi army
was killed on the eastern front so who
actually defeated the nazis was it the
russians or the allies of the us
good question
so as we know the russians bled a lot in
the second world war and a lot of the
fighting was actually primarily done by
the soviet union by the russians it was
stalin and his army that was at the
forefront of much of the fighting
against the nazis of course i am not
trying to take away from the
achievements of the allies in the united
states after as we know the tide turned
after the us entered the fray in the
second world war so they took care of
liberating uh western europe france etc
the invasion of normandy etc
and uh in the in the pacific theater as
well defeating japan we know how they
did that
uh but when it comes to the continental
yeah the continent of europe much of the
fighting was done by the soviets
i believe that at the end of the second
world war once the war was over i think
about 80 percent of the people of europe
actually
credited the ussr for saving them from
the nazis but eventually what happened
is that over time
the propaganda machine took over the u.s
propaganda machine decor which well why
would they not do it and of course they
had this very powerful tool called
hollywood
so
because of their their actions because
of uh
because of all the propaganda they put
out the kind of movies they made it was
made to appear as if it was the us that
was the only primary actor
in world war two and in defeating
the uh nazis so that is not quite the
case a significant
amount of fighting and winning was done
by the ussr i would say that the
majority of the fighting in europe was
actually done by the ussr and it's the
ussr that actually defeated nazi germany
i mean who was the which was the first
power to enter
berlin
uh when it is believed that uh committed
suicide it was the soviet union so
that's what it is history isn't exactly
the way you're taught it and the way the
movie's portrayed the truth is something
different
let's take another question
uh this is by pragyan chakrabarty was
uzbekistan kazakhstan tajikistan etc
part of greater iran
uh i don't know the map with me right
now you know i love the map but if you
talk about greater iran
tajikistan would certainly be part of
the greater iran the iranians would even
consider western afghanistan or maybe
even the whole afghanistan to be part of
greater iran
and certainly the caucasus region
so all of that is what they consider to
be part of iran i would not say that
uzbekistan
kazakhstan etc are part of greater iran
because those are turkic
nations
but the truth is this that before iran
was even a thing
all of this what is now called central
asia was part of greater india
it was
that's the two name
names for the entire
large expanse of central asia
one was the name of the expanse above
north of the himalayas including tibet
and the tharin river
region present day so called xinjiang
which is currently occupied by china and
of course the
western regions of central asia between
present-day xinjiang and eastern europe
all of that also so all of that was
indianized there were multiple waves of
migration out of india thousands of
years before today many of these waves
have been recorded in ancient vedic
literature
so even before iran or persia was a
thing the entirety of central asia was
indic in nature
there were kingdoms and dynasties that
originated out of india
and
what we see today is not reflective
the the demographic makeup of central
asia today is very different it's
because of what happened in the past
1000 years
uh
the turks conquered central asia there
were terrible massacres and there was
essentially a population replacement
event
and the present-day people of central
asia
are kind of a combination
you know a mixture
an ethnic admixture of the
old kitchen and
indic populations and the turks the
majority of the well you could say
contribution genetic contribution would
be turkic so that's what happened so yes
some parts of this are considered to be
part of greater iran but before iran was
even a thing it was all part of greater
india so that's the answer now let's
take another question
this is by ishan sood
is elon musk's move
of buying twitter does it indicate his
plans to explicitly support republicans
and or through democrats in the next
election what will be the geopolitical
implications well elon musk is making
curious statements on social media
on twitter
firstly his acquisition of twitter is
not yet a done deal he seems to be uh
he seems to be showing some amount of
buyers remorse or regret i mean it's not
yet officially uh
accomplished
and what it seems what he seems to have
discovered is that a significant
proportion of the
users
on twitter the account on twitter could
be bought accounts which means that they
don't really
represent real human beings these are
accounts that people have created that
certain
people or powers or whatever have
created in order to uh to manipulate
public opinion and achieve a variety of
objectives so the figure that elon musk
is talking about is that anything
between 20 and maybe even 70 80 percent
of the users on twitter are not actually
real human beings so that's what he's
talking about
so that is the kind of rough waters the
deal has run into the twitter board is
saying nothing doing we're gonna go
ahead with this thing and we don't must
be able to pay the actual uh 44 billion
dollar amount and he cannot go back on
his valuation and so on so far so
there's a back and forth going on right
now well the thing is that elon musk has
recently uh indicated his support for
the republican party uh
on twitter he said that he always voted
democrat but now the things are such
that he
is more inclined to or he has decided to
vote republican
so what does this indicate see elon musk
is one of the most influential people on
the planet whatever he says has real
world
implications and repercussions if he
says uh if he supports a certain company
or stock that stock goes up in valuation
if he disparages a certain company that
stock plummets the same goes with
cryptocurrencies bitcoin etc and now if
he is talking about the republicans and
saying he'll vote republican
it's possible that there could be a sway
in his supporters who may have been
democrats who may possibly want to think
about voting republican next time so it
is a politically loaded and charged
statement that he has made and it has
real world implications uh what is the
question does it mean that he wants to
overthrow
the democrats in the next election i
don't
think that he actually wants to
overthrow the democrats or any such
thing he's simply indicating his
dissatisfaction and disillusionment
with the democratic party and that's
what he's that's what he's expressing i
believe
maybe he doesn't or maybe he does he's a
very smart person maybe he does realize
what what in real world repercussions
his state statements have maybe it's a
pressure tactic to get the democratic
party which is currently in power to to
do things better or what so i'm not
quite sure what his what his intentions
are i don't think it's an attempt to
overthrow any party but it's certainly
very influential now the bigger picture
is that elon musk has yet gotten
embroiled in this entire twitter matter
he has
well essentially gone ahead with this
acquisition of twitter
the question is what is he trying to do
the guy
has very big very big dreams and a very
big vision he wants to take humanity to
mars
he wants to uh
he wants the world to
move to electric power instead of fossil
fuels and he's doing it via his uh
soul i mean electric power vehicles and
all that which does
have a have a certain amount of
ecological footprint because of the of
the batteries but
he's go he's making moves in the right
direction he's also he's got the solar
power company and he's got the boring
company as well so he has
enormous ambitions and he's got a very
big vision
the question is what is he trying to
achieve by by also fighting by opening
one more front and fighting one more
battle which is the very political very
visible battle over twitter
i i understand that he believes in free
speech he's a free speech absolutist but
is it
advisable is it is it wise for one
person to fight so many battles
the dreams that he has are already
enormous dreams it would be a miracle if
you can achieve all of them
he could very well be in the path of of
doing that eventually in the next 10 or
so years
getting people on mars and all that it's
possible he has he already has the
technology my question is why is he
trying to fight so many battles
especially these
these political battles so i'm not quite
sure what he's trying to do does this
have geopolitical
uh does it have a geopolitical angle
see spacex
is at the forefront of space exploration
and space uh exploration technology
which means it is a very valuable ascent
in the us geopolitical arsenal if the
u.s is to um
is to conquer
outer space and beat all the other
nations in doing it spacex will play a
very big role in that
and
spacex also launches multiple
a variety of secret satellites military
satellites that have military
applications so spacex is very much part
of the jigsaw puzzle in geopolitics and
elon musk is very much part of that
because he is the guy who owns spacex so
there is always a geopolitical angle to
whatever elon musk does whether he likes
it or not it's there
so clearly this twitter battle also
could have
some kind of geopolitical angle i'm not
sure if he
if he is doing it uh on his own volition
or or
what the thing is but clearly
twitter is
is an instrument
that influences
a significant population percentage of
the world's population world leaders use
it and
your data is is essentially
open
it's it's open to the us government
whether you know it or not whether you
like it or not so it is a very powerful
geopolitical tool
and uh so yeah i'm not sure what elon
musk is trying to do so that's something
that i am not able to decipher thus far
but it i find it strange that somebody
with such enormous
ambitions is trying to fight so many
battles some of them could actually be
considered or characterized as somewhat
petty battles so i'm not sure if his ego
has got to his head or if this is a very
well calculated very well thought out
strategy time will tell us but right now
it's i find it kind of puzzling
okay next question
this is my learning and recreation is it
possible for an ias officer to bring
change to in in india
uh from the perspective of fake history
and bring out truth in books
see the thing is this ias officers as
long as they are active in their duty
they are essentially tools of the state
they are not expected or even supposed
to have a leadership
position in society they are simply
tools of the government the government
tells them what to do and they carry out
the government's wishes that's all it is
they do not decide
grand strategy or grant policy
they will be told what to do and they
will decide how to carry that out and
how to achieve those objectives or
whatever the demands of the politicians
are
that's what iis officers do as such they
have no role in changing the content of
history textbooks or bringing out any
bringing about any revolution in society
or
bringing out bringing up truths in books
that is a political decision if the
syllabus is going to be changed if the
books are going to be
decontaminated of all the fake history
and distortions it's not going to happen
at the is level it's going to happen at
the political level some political
leader of this country is going to have
to show the courage and the vision
and the gumption to to carry to see this
through to first of all decide to do
this and then see this through so once
the decision is made maybe ias
officers will be involved in
implementing the decision and ensuring
it is done properly
and it still remains to be said if they
will actually do it properly because
well that's a whole different story so
this leadership has to come from the
politicians it has to come at the
political level not at the is level iis
officers are simply bureaucrats they are
they i am sure there are many fantastic
people among the iis qatar i'm sure
there are very good people very
nationalistic patriotic people and all
that but their function is to carry out
orders and not provide any leadership if
an is officer starts taking decisions
that the politicians are not approved
that is actually a big problem they're
not supposed to do that so we should not
expect any such
change coming in from the iis level that
is always going to be a political
decision
this is a question by abhijit abhijit
at the end
the question is is it possible to create
an empire in in the modern day
how were empires formed in the first
place
how do people know about it if it is
formed do people fall for it or support
it
so the question is how do you form an
empire in the modern day is an empire
even possible in the 21st century well
you already have an empire in the 21st
century
there is one single superpower in the
world that controls most of the world's
economy policy decision making all the
institute institutions of the world like
the world bank imf
imf etc and it essentially has the
ability to intervene in any part of the
world militarily at 30 to 60 minutes
notice that is the united states we call
it a superpower but it's actually an
empire it has military bases all across
the world
in a very large number of countries
there are certain countries where it has
permanent military bases for decades it
has had this military bases for decades
south korea is an example japan is an
example germany is an example it has
nuclear weapons on the soil of other
countries so this is an empire
we call it a superpower these days which
is the acceptable terminology but it is
nothing but an empire so an empire is
very much possible today and all these
countries which are supposedly free
democratic countries like the uk like
all of the eu nations the nato members
like like japan like south korea
australia new zealand
these are supposedly free democratic
countries with for with their own
foreign policies these are actually u.s
for some states their foreign policy is
essentially dictated by the us and all
of their uh
well whatever happens there it happens
under u.s oversight more or less whether
you realize it or not so we have an
empire in the modern day it's the u.s
empire which is a continuation of the
british empire
what happened is that the capital city
like i've spoken before the the
focal point of the british empire was
london
all we have to do is to reframe that as
the anglo-saxon empire
the english-speaking empire the
anglo-phone empire or the anglo-saxon
empire all that happened is that the
headquarters moved from london to
washington dc that's all that happened
everything else is the same so we have
an empire today how do empires form how
are they created
all you have to do is look up how the
roman empire came into existence how the
gupta empire came into existence how the
mauryan empire how the kushan empire of
the chula empire came into existence
usually it is through military conquest
that's what usually happens when it
comes to the roman empire it was all
about military expansion relentless
military expansion when it came to the
um when it comes to the uh british
empire it was all about relentless
military expansion and colonization and
and destruction of the colonized lands
and so on so that is a pattern that you
see over and over again when it comes to
indian empires it's always
again been about military expansion but
it has not been about colonization so
the chula has conquered the entirety of
southeast asia more or less there was no
colonization and extraction of resources
from there so that is something indians
or the dharmic people did not ever do
but it's always about military expansion
so if a new empire is to emerge
in let's say the 21st century which is
different from the anglo-saxon empire it
is obviously going to be through
military conquest now in the 21st
century military doesn't necessarily
mean kinetic conquest it could be done
through cyber conquest that is also a
possibility so as technology evolves
the definition of conquest may change
and you may not have human uh soldiers
involved in that and not much kinetic
action but you may still have uh
a conquest that takes place so so that's
how empires are formed uh will people
fall for it or support it i mean will
people oppose it or support it who
opposes the anglo-saxon empire very few
people very few people are aware of it
in the future if a new empire does rise
it could be termed in the appropriate
manner
instead of calling it an empire we call
it it's a new superpower that grows and
then people are okay with that words
are all that that's required to to set
people's minds at ease
if you you may do the worst kind of
actions but if you
couch it in the right terminology it's
all acceptable
so uh public opinion is actually quite
easy to manipulate because of the power
of
of a technology
so yeah it's it would be very much
possible for people to
to afford to to make people accept it
and see it as something good and it a
new empire may not necessarily be
something bad so it all depends on who
is creating the new empire and what
means are they using and what are their
policies
okay next question is by kiran raj
what is marxism
is it bad so marxism is an ideology you
could
you could arrange a week-long seminar
about marxism eight hours per day or
eight hours per day for seven days that
sort of thing in order to describe what
marxism is and go and go into detail
about what it is i mean you bring a
bunch of marxist academics together
they're to go on for hours and days and
weeks about what marxism is but
from a non-marxist perspective what is
marxism it's an ideology
it's a political viewpoint it's so it's
a kind of worldview
and
instead of going into what the
characteristics are and what it says and
what kind of world it envisages we can
take a different approach and look at
the real world consequences of marxism
we've had marxism in existence for about
a century and a half in the past hundred
or so years you've had marxist
governments coming to power
and the marxist takeovers of countries
and what you see
the real world effect of marxism is it
marxism and based on that you can
characterize marxism thusly
marxism is a socio-political toolkit
whose only objective is to concentrate
all power
and resources in the hands of a very
small number of people which is
typically the politburo
of the local communist party so all of
the power all of the uh
all of the
wealth etc is
eventually concentrated in the hands of
a very small group of people they are
the ones who hold all the power they
call it the dictatorship of the
proliterate or whatever and they said
that we represent the people but there's
never any there's never been any
democracy in marxism so that is what
marxism is i'm not saying it is bad or
good that's what the world has seen
that's what the pattern has been in the
past 100 years it's always the same
thing after a so-called marxist
revolution eventually after this dust
settled down settles down what we find
is that all of this power and all of the
uh assets of the country and all of the
wealth of the country eventually ends up
in the possession of a very small group
of people that's what always happens now
is it bad is it good i mean if the group
of people who acquires all of this
wealth and power
has good intentions then it could
actually transform society in a good way
but it's never happened thus far and
what the marxists say is that you know
they have never implemented marxism
properly for the past hundred years
they've done it again and again but
they've never implemented properly so
bring them to power and i and i will
show you what real maxism is so that's
that's the refrain that you hear
constantly from marxist thinkers and
advocates
but it's never ever worked out like that
and there is no guarantee that the next
iteration of marxism is also going to
produce good results it is ever going to
produce good results but
clearly it's the kind of thing it's the
kind of social political toolkit that
ends up concentrating all the wealth and
the power in a very small group of
people in case a good group of people is
able to use this toolkit and acquire the
power then they may be able to use it
for the right purposes so there are some
people who call themselves proponents of
dharmic marxism well i wish them all the
best and all the luck and if they are
able to come to power let's see how
dharmic they end up being because you
know
you may be the best
person in the world but when you acquire
that amount of power and
wealth
usually it goes to your head and yeah
the results are never that good there is
the scene in the lord of the rings
in the in which there is this great
wizard called gandalf gandalf
and the the protagonist frodo offers the
great ring the one ring to gamble please
take it i cannot it's too great for me
it's too big of a burden for me but
gandalf you take it and gandalf says i
dare not take it through me it would
wield a power too great and too terrible
to behold so that's the kind of thing
you know you need to know what wealth
and power can do to you and when you so
so that's a
i think that's what marxism does
possibly many of these
marxists have good ideas and have good
intentions but when they actually get
all the power in the wealth they may end
up using it in the wrong way so that's
what the world has always seen next
question
uh the question is please explain why
the harappans buried the dead while we
burned them we is in hindus
also they lived in brick made houses
while we had huts how to counter the
card the the argument of our invasion
does it indicate we are audience so we
follow different methods okay i'm going
to answer the question about the burials
all the other stuff i've answered
multiple times
okay so yes we find burials in the sapta
region from the harappan period of our
civilization right that's what we call
the harappan phase or the indus valley
phase or the saraswati sindhu phase of
india's civilization and we find burials
there we find cemeteries in some places
but where individuals have been buried
do you know that even today in in
hinduism there is burial
most people create that they're dead yes
but certain individuals are buried there
are certain communities like the
lingayats i believe who practice
burial instead of cremation and when it
comes to
great personalities like saints
essentially who die or who who leave the
mortal coil so to say they are buried
it's called samadhi you go to places
like sumnat et cetera like uh what's the
place where prabhas patan you will find
lots and lots of these samadhis of great
hindu saints so these are burials you
can call it a samadhi you can call it
whatever you want
it is a burial so
uh imagine this scenario that all the
individuals you find buried in these
cemeteries in the sundu region from that
phase of our civilization maybe they
were saints were buried um
in in the form of samadhi of course at
the former when you when someone goes to
samadhi typically or or sometimes they
will be put in the padmasana pose
sitting pose but it's also possible that
you may be uh
placed into samadhi
while lying down as if it's a burial so
it is there is a possibility we have to
uh
take seriously
and there is no guarantee that everybody
was buried we find a few burials
but we also find plots with cremated
ashes and burnt bones inside which
indicates that there were cremations as
well
the question is what was prevalent where
cremation is prevalent or where burials
prevalent we still don't have the answer
so once we do a lot more archaeology we
will be able to answer this question as
of now it is i can say that it is in no
way uh dissonant with what hinduism is
in hinduism we have all kinds of
practices including variance so that
does not say in any way this is not
hinduism and this is not uh whatever
aryan whatever the myth is this is very
much part of indian civilization there
is no doubt whatsoever about that the
next question is
can india get her historical lands back
without any global backlash is there a
way this question is in context with the
russia ukraine war as russia is now
completely alienated or isolated by
western countries economically because
of its actions in ukraine
so is there
a way for india to take back her lands
which were historically part of india
without uh inviting a global backlash as
of today there is no such way as of
today because india is not one of the
top two powers in the world
right militarily and economically
today if you do anything that goes
against the u.s
vision of the world order you're gonna
face severe consequences and that's what
we are seeing with the russia ukraine
situation the russia the russian economy
has been completely cut off and the
russians are taking measures to
to alleviate the problem but that's what
the americans have attempted to do
they've attempted to destroy the russian
economy right by imposing
the entire bucket load of sanctions on
russia
if india were to invade pakistan today
or or some other country let's say
hypothetically right there will be a
similar situation that's what they did
with iraq as well they first let saddam
hussein believe that it was okay for him
to invade kuwait and when he went ahead
with the invasion
he was destroyed his country was
destroyed that's what happened we are
seeing something similar with russia of
course russia is a whole different beast
it's not a tiny nation like a
reasonably weak nation like iraq used to
be
uh it's a superpower in its own right
especially because of its nuclear
arsenal now if india were to do such a
thing india would face the same
situation
there would certainly be a whole slew of
economic sanctions impose upon india
and maybe there could be some military
action as well if the u.s so desires the
u.s is way way way more powerful than
india is as of today right so as of
today there is no way for india to
reclaim its historical lands through
military action without inviting a
global backlash especially from the
so-called
first world which is the u.s empire
so what does india need to do well india
needs to build up its economy it's it's
economic strength it's military strength
india needs to reach at least the 10
trillion dollar uh mark from from the
gdp perspective that's the first thing
indians need to do it's a long-term game
it's a long-term game we need to be
patient right
so when should india go ahead and
reclaim its territories well when there
is no impediment to doing so
i have said this in the past and say it
again there is this movie this marvel
universe movie in which there is this
character called thanos he says i am
individual
well india should do this when india
becomes inevitable so the real
trick is to become inevitable you become
inevitable when you are the biggest
shark in the scene
so that's what needs to happen as of
today india should not think about
reacquiring lost territories what india
should think about is solving the
pakistan issue or certain other issues
and there are multiple creative ways of
doing it geopolitically so that is step
number one reacquiring those territories
is a long term is a long term uh
project
because culturally those territories are
completely
different from indian culture i mean
it's culturally it's become something
else entirely right
so uh it's a long-term project it's not
gonna happen overnight it's gonna not
gonna happen
in the next five years or ten years but
it will happen eventually when india
becomes inevitable so all of you need to
work together to make india inevitable
the next question is by donggasingtohan
scientists have for the first time grown
seeds on lunar soil collected by nasa
what are your views on this will it be
possible in the future to grow plants at
the moon
yes i read the news recently that
scientists have grown plants on lunar
soil it seems that the the plants don't
necessarily thrive or prosper on lunar
soil but they are able to to grow only
the soil they don't love it but they're
able to survive on it which is excellent
because in the future if we want to have
human colonies on the moon then we will
need to if it's going to be a long-term
colony if it's going to be a five-year
colony we don't want to
get supplies every three months from
from from the earth it's very expensive
to send a rocket all the way to the moon
so instead of that if we can uh
create a greenhouse kind of structure on
the moon with atmosphere with air and
use the local lunar soil in which to
grow plants that would solve a whole lot
of problems right so we could actually
if this works create entire farms
on the moon
and we could grow a variety of food
crops so it's a very good thing uh it's
it's very promising uh and if you can
perhaps treat the soil in some manner
and make it more fertile or more
conducive to making plants happier that
would be great but the initial news is
very promising it's it's very it's very
it's very good
so it means that we will be able to
solve this very major issue once we are
able to have a long-term maybe even
permanent settlements on the moon we'll
be able to blow grow plants there
locally and when it comes to the lunar
gravity i think plants will definitely
grow in a different way or at least
they'll be able to survive and let's see
how the seeds and
and all that comes out but it's it's a
it's a very promising and great
development in my opinion
okay the next question is by priyank
soni why did chess emerge quite late in
india
even though the origin of chess was from
india itself
i'm not sure what you mean by just
emerged late in india
uh i don't know what wikipedia says or
encyclopedia britannica or whatever says
about chess in india what we
know is the evidence that we have and
the oldest evidence of chess in india
oldest known evidence for chess in india
is this chess board with just pieces
which is from i think it is it was found
in
lothal which is a saraswati hindu
site archaeological site it's in gujarat
in western india right so that's where
this chess board was found it's a chess
board and some chess pieces have also
been found and i would imagine i don't
have the exact dates with me right now
right here but i that era was about 5000
years before today so that
that chess
uh chess set would most likely date
between six thousand and four thousand
years before today which is quite old
and it already tells you it tells you
that just was already a thing it was a
very well developed game
with proper chess board and chess pieces
and the same
most likely similar rules to what we
have today
so it demonstrates actually that chess
is very old uh if if this chess set is
from 5000 years before today
most likely just must have developed at
least a thousand years before that
so it tells you how old jess is and
obviously chess
emerged out of india i'm not sure what
wikipedia says maybe they say chess came
from somewhere else we don't care about
that we have the evidence it shows that
just was being played 5000 or so years
before today in india itself and similar
situations occur with other sports for
instance the sport of polo comes to my
mind now
i remember reading in wikipedia three or
four years ago that the origin of polo
seems to be from iran
that's not the case
polo originates as far as i know in
eastern india in the far east of india
in manipur the world's oldest polar
ground is in imphal which is the capital
of manipur it's at least 2000 years old
this oldest polar ground
and uh
it's the british who came to india and
who called who who
eventually uh
occupied manipur in beginning 1891 and
they observed this sport that the the
people of manipur would play
and they copied it and for some reason
they called it polo and they also
started playing it and that's how
the sport
spread throughout europe and the english
speaking world and all that it's
possible that the persians may also have
been playing a similar game but clearly
the origin is in india the same goes for
for like i said jess and maybe even for
kabaddi the iranians are also quite good
at playing kabaddi there are
so many uh similarities in this
in
between india and persia and obviously
india is the older civilization persia
is about three three and a half maybe
four thousand years old but it came out
of india the oldest the
founders of persia were indians who
migrated eastward
so uh to summarize chess is a very
ancient game which came out of india so
is polo so is kabaddi and so is like i
would say games like coco etc uh which i
don't know so much about but for chess
and polo i'm certain
india is the place of origin
okay
next question
it's by krishna can you give a brief
summary of the kaczynski manifesto
manifesto
so the kaczynski manifesto is called
the industrial revolution and
i don't quite remember the title of the
manifesto so what is this kazinski
manifesto who is ted kaczynski ted
kaczynski is a genius level
mathematician he is also a convicted
terrorist
right
so
i'm not sure if it was the 50s of the
60s that he went to howard i think even
he went to one of the ivy league
universities
he did a phd he was very young
and he published a number of papers in
pure mathematics he is a
high high quality mathematician and then
for some reason uh
he
started displaying some anti-social
tendencies that's what they say and he
isolated himself he went into the he cut
cut himself off from most human contact
he
acquired a cabin
in the woods secluded cabin in a
secluded part of the woods and uh he
would he did not have any internet
obviously
there was no internet no electricity no
modern amenities and that's where where
he would live for months on end
and
he turned out to be the person who was
known as the yuna bomber so there was
this person in the u.s would male
who would send parcels containing bombs
to various people
and a number of people died because that
some people lost their fingers and eye
or whatever that sort of thing some
people actually died so he would mail
out these bombs these
pipe bombs or cylinder bombs in parcels
and when the person would open it that
person would
be exposed to the explosion so that's
what he did
and he wrote a lengthy manifesto and
mailed it to
some prominent newspapers in the u.s and
uh it was published
it's known as the unabomber manifesto
and eventually this this guy was
he was tracked down and apprehended and
he's serving a life sentence in prison
so
it looks like he will spend the rest of
his days in prison he's already quite
elderly
so so that's what it is so what was this
manifesto it was a manifesto railing
against the modernization and
industrialization of society so i
haven't read the thing in detail but
that's what i can do tell you about it
and the thing is this
i mean i have read parts of it a long
time ago so i don't remember the
specifics
but
what i can tell you is that it makes a
whole lot of sense what he wrote
but what he did doesn't make sense i
mean those what was the point of killing
random people maybe he it was not random
maybe he selected people
uh based on certain specific uh
traits or whatever
but
what was the point of killing innocent
people who he did not even really know
in person
maybe he was sending out a message or
whatever but his reaction to
what he saw as this terrible direction
the society is taking in his reaction
was not right obviously it's not right
to indulge in terrorist activities or
murder people but if you read the
manifesto it makes a whole lot of sense
it's as relevant in the 21st century in
in 2022 as it was when it was written
so
if you are curious read it it's not
going to turn you into a terrorist but
be aware that the person who wrote it
ended up doing this terrible
these terrible acts so that is the the
unabomber manifesto or the kasinsky
manifesto i don't remember the specifics
so you can look it up it's available
online
krishna not says is the world really
dying
the world is never dying the world is
always in a state of flux it's always
changing and change also certainly does
manifest itself in the form of death
deaths and then
organisms die
people die and then there is rebirth in
a variety of ways new organisms emerge
new people are born uh species
come and go
the dinosaurs were a thing they are no
longer a thing of course they're still
out there i can hear them sometimes you
know but uh the non-avian dinosaurs died
lots of species came and went and some
many of them did not even leave a trace
in the fossil record especially the
species that were soft-bodied species
without without without bones you know
so is the world dying the world is
changing
i'm sure you asking this in the context
of climate change in the current
scenario the situation in the
environment where you have we're in the
middle of an ongoing extinction event
no none of the extinction events that
happened in the past mass mass
extinctions happened overnight even the
uh 66 million years before today
extinction event event the cretaceous
paleogene extinction event did not
happen
overnight or 24 hours it took
a certain period of time maybe ten years
or so there was this uh impact event the
chips
uh asteroid of comment the impact and
also the deccan traps volcanism which
both contributed to what happened but
there have been many mass extinctions
and these mass extinctions they happen
over time it doesn't happen in a weekend
so we are currently seeing an
accelerated extinction of a variety of
species so that's happening and much of
that is
caused by human meddling
by human middling in the environment by
the
by the changes we have brought into the
environment by the carbon we have
released into the atmosphere we are the
record highs of carbon carbon particles
in the atmosphere we are dumping
untold amounts of garbage sewage plastic
into the oceans we have
we have deforested much of the planet it
is still going on
99 of the biomass non-human biomass on
the surface of the planet is
agricultural animals
100 years ago 99 of the non-human
biomass was wild animals so we have
brought about so many changes
and
this is going to have consequences now
whether it's going to be good in the
long run or not remains to be seen
obviously there's going to be
detrimental deleterious effects for us
for our descendants and for the other
species
maybe
it is certainly
possible that there could be a new mass
extinction there is certainly a mass
extinction going on many non-human
species are going extinct
at an alarming rate but it could end up
destroying us as a species as well it's
possible that in the next
three to four hundred maybe 500 years
humanity itself may go extinct it is a
possibility does it mean the world is
dying no the world will do just fine no
matter what we do the world will survive
the world will evolve
there have been times when 95 of the
species of the planet died out for
whatever reason and yet the planet
bounced back new species emerged the
process took tens of millions of years
but it happens
so from our perspective tens of millions
of years is unimaginable we can put the
figure down write it down but it doesn't
really make sense to us that that number
of years
so we have been around for a fraction of
the time
300 000 or so years as a species right
so it's possible we may go extinct but
the world will just will do just fine
new species will eventually emerge
whatever destruction or or degradation
we are causing to the environment will
eventually
uh
be become part of the planet the
environment will heal itself with or
without us and it will go on
so the world is not dying it is changing
and we are contributing significantly to
the change some people say that climate
change is another thing that's not true
climate has always been changing but
right now some of the contribution to
climate change or
a non-trivial contribution to the
current climate change is coming from us
it's not coming from us in india it's
something that's been going on since the
industrial revolution to 300 years or so
before today it's all been done if you
want to a proportion blame it's been
done by the west and now they're trying
to put the blame on india and china and
the developing world which is not going
to worship us but that's a different
issue so the the answer is the world is
not dying the world is changing and it's
going to do just fine with or without us
we are just a small
very small
interlude or small chapter in the
history of our planet the next question
is by saurabh
is ancient greek literature totally
reliable especially in the indian
context as we know
everyone glorifies their own culture
rather than other cultures okay
so greek uh
ancient greek literature
is important in the indian context and
the reason why greek literature and
tibetan literature and chinese
literature and the persian literature
arabic literature etc why is it
important it's because we have lost our
own writings
our ancestors compiled voluminous
collections of books and writings these
were stored in the great libraries in
our great universities and these were
all wiped out about a thousand years ago
everything was burned down so we lost
the written records of our history and
because of this enormous massive loss we
are now forced to rely on foreign
accounts of india written by foreign
travelers to india
people like shwanzang fahia and from
china
who was it
various various greek travelers
there are a couple of squeaky accounts
as well and various other accounts like
that foreign foreign accounts of india
so the question is about uh greek
accounts of of of india ancient india so
one of the examples is the periplus of
the era 3 and c i don't remember who the
author is but it talks about the
geography of india and who the
kings are it it mentions a king called
which is clearly the great indus
and so on it talks about the geography
of india the major seas cities
some rivers and so on then there is
obviously the indica of megasthenes
magastaris was a greek ambassador to
india he was an ambassador
in the mauryan court
and he wrote a very interesting account
of india it was written from a
tactical military kind of perspective
you know facts and figures facts and
figures facts and figures that sort of
thing
and now this account is called
indica the indica
that account is lost we don't have the
original writing at all
anymore
but we know
to some extent what was written in
indica because it has been referenced
and mentioned and in some cases uh
reproduced to some extent in other
writings
in the writings of other greek writers
of scholars or historians who mentioned
what magastan is wrote and they have
kind of
repeated that to some extent so that's
why we know some portion of what he
wrote now clearly these are foreign
accounts they will have a foreign
perspective whether it's a greek
perspective or chinese perspective or a
skit
perspective or or an arabic perspective
or persian perspective or later european
perspective we know how badly the
europeans distorted indian culture and
history it's something we are still
coping with now at least we have we are
able to understand the extent
of
how badly they mischaracterized indian
culture and distorted industry they
did that on purpose
because they had a certain
objective right to re-engineer indian
society not which is still a work in
progress now the greeks may not have had
that sort of thing but they would
certainly have their own foreign
perspective so the same goes with the
chinese and other accounts so you can
never
rely
on any of these accounts entirely you
cannot take them at face value
but what we can do is we take
a big picture
perspective and look at all the accounts
of all these different foreigners who
came from different parts of the world
and then try to
draw the patterns that emerge out of
that so certain patterns will repeat
themselves in the accounts of all of
these foreigners and that is something
you can trust if all of them agree about
certain things those things at least we
can trust so that's why we you need a
big picture perspective you cannot just
rely on one person's account of india
because it's gonna reflect that person's
uh perspective and possibly even biases
or or their ignorance also of local
customs so they may see it in a
different way
and that may not be entirely correct so
you have to take a big picture
perspective that's why you need books
that uh
you need
books that could possibly offer a big
picture perspective from the
360 degree view so you can't rely on one
on any one account but when certain
patterns emerge from all the accounts
that certainly is something you can rely
on okay i think i've run out of
questions for now
so i'm gonna stop it here just a brief
recorded session of ask abhijit as
always thank you for watching and
this weekend i will do it live
until then take care and thank you very
much for watching and keep asking your
questions bye